[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
relativity relativity means special
relativity
mostly and then at the end a little bit
a little bit of general relativity but
general relativity done uh with some uh
not rigor so much as well conceptual
rigor if not mathematical rigor now
before I go ahead let me just tell you
one thing I'm going to be gone for two
weeks I have to be in Israel I have to
give some lectures uh to
the I don't know to somebody
uh uh some organization of
philosophers and uh so I will be gone
for two
weeks that means I think does anybody
have a calendar in their head I'm coming
back on the 24th but I don't know what
date that is yeah yeah yeah yeah but we
will continue we will we will get 10
full classes even if we have to go uh
into the um into June a little bit we'll
get 10 full classes but I will uh
necessarily have to stagger them a bit
yeah how about the
um lecture oh oh yes
uh that's also on Monday isn't it yep so
you going next two weeks yeah I'll be
I'll be gone for the next two weeks one
after that M well you know if there's
enough if there's
flexibility if there's flexibility about
the day of the week we could just when a
thing like that happens say well we will
meet on Wednesday instead of on Monday
or something like that uh I know s some
people arrange their schedule one way or
another and it doesn't fit um
but we will have one class before the
houseat lecture and then we can decide
what I think so I think it's this one no
no I think there's another one I think
the 20 uh oh wait wait wait wait wait
well if nothing else the Hof electure I
think begins at 8 oh there's a problem
there uh I may have to be
available well one way or
another the next two Mondays H you'll be
going I'll be going the next two Mondays
and then I'll be
back let's assume we will meet here on
the Monday after I get back that's the
30th 30th that's the H that's the 30th
that's the Hof lecture I will be I will
be here okay now I am also the host for
the Huff lecture so this is going to
this so you know what it'll probably
mean is we'll go to the hle lecture but
I won't I'm not going to count that as a
regular class uh if we do that and we'll
see at that time we'll see if we can
figure out a time to uh some way to make
adjustments um just make you know one
suggestion on that is that in the past
when that kind of a conflict came you
just made the starter class at six
instead of seven we never did that did
we yeah yeah we did did we
we can do that oh you mean you mean
specifically for the yeah yeah we could
do that that uh okay good good good
let's let's do that yeah yeah all right
so let's uh let's assume that on the
week after I return that we meet
here the Monday after we return we meet
here at 6 does that work for
everybody okay good 30th I think it's
the 30th yeah yeah but then we but then
I would like to find uh maybe some ways
of I'm always in the situation where I
have to be someplace else I have to be
two places at the same time and uh it's
hard to do so if we can somehow juggle
times that uh that does help
me
little yeah more than a little uncertain
most of the time all right when you were
talking about the next term you mean
summer or no no no I no no summer I
summer I uh I I won't teach H you're
somewhere else no I'm actually usually
here but uh no I need uh I need to stop
and do nothing for the summer I need to
think about
things all right Let's do let's begin
with special
relativity and let's really do the
mathematics of special relativity
carefully let's work it out uh work out
the
details of energy momentum well first
we're going to work out the details of
space and time and
SpaceTime the details and symmetries
wrench
Transformations uh what it means for
things to be synchronous and so forth to
work these things out with some care and
some
precision and then move on to we could
call that
kinematics kinematics space and time how
things move but not why they move then
comes the question why things move and
why things move is because of
forces and forces of course are the
subject of Dynamics and so we will study
a little bit about the Dynamics of
special relativity energy momentum Force
the analog of Newton's equations not
Newton's gravitational equations but
Newton's equations of motion for special
relativity eal MC squared and all that
stuff what it means and I think that
should probably take us about five
lectures five or six or something like
that then I would move on to some
general relativity the general
relativity that we'll do will not be
incorrect it will be absolutely correct
but what I will teach less of is the
Einstein field equations and more of
what happens to particles and objects
when they're in a given gravitational
field all right so what is a grait
ational field curvature of
SpaceTime and that kind of thing without
trying to get into the harder much more
difficult subject of solving Einstein's
field equations that's hard it's hard
for me anyway
[Music]
so that's what we'll do this quarter
basic
relativity special and a bit of General
we'll probably get we'll probably get to
the point where we can uh talk about
black holes a little bit
maybe also get to the point where we can
talk about expansion of the universe
some of the uh some of the interesting
things that flow out
of uh the special the general theory of
relativity all right now um let's
begin first of all what do we mean by
relativity special well what do we mean
by relativity in general what we mean by
relativity is the idea that of course
all of you know that the laws of
physics are independent of the frame of
reference in which you study them frame
of reference simply for our purposes
here means a state of
motion of a set of coordinates if you
like the way to think about it is to
imagine space being filled up with a
lattice an imaginary lattice of meters
sticks so that every point in space is
labeled by a uh x a y and a z a set of
meter sticks and at each vertex of the
lattice a
clock and the clock measures time now in
Newtonian physics in Newtonian physics
Newton imagined that time was very very
Universal you imagine God's time God's
time was the same for
everybody uh there was no question of
what the time was on a particular clock
Clocks Were synchronized it didn't
matter how they moved it didn't matter
how you move it didn't matter how you
move with your watch or without your
watch everybody would agree at every
instant at every place in the world on
what the time is T that of course had to
be given
up uh when when Einstein moved to
special
relativity but the idea of Relativity
was already there before Einstein long
before Einstein it basically goes back
to Galileo so let me just remind you
what Galilean relativity is how it how
and why it
failed uh the way I like to think about
relativity is I like to imagine I always
like to have a picture in my head uh
that I
can uh uh think about intuitively and
the picture that I have on my head in my
head is the same one that Einstein
thought about moving along in a railroad
train uh with in a railroad which is
extremely well made so well made that
the tracks are perfectly smooth so
smooth that the train doesn't rattle it
doesn't shake and it just moves with
absolute uniform
velocity now what are the laws of
physics well my favorite description of
the laws of physics in this train is
what I like to imagine the laws of
juggling juggling is a is good physics
incidentally you to be a good juggler
you have to have a very very good sense
of timing you have to have a good sense
of gravity you have to have a good sense
of a lot of different aspects of physics
of course you don't you may not
consciously be using those but at least
unconsciously all kinds of physics comes
into juggling
so there are some rules you throw the
ball up and you wait a certain amount of
time and you catch it and you transfer
and you do whatever it is that you're
supposed to do and you call all of those
the laws of uh the laws of physics or
the laws of juggling now it's a fact of
nature that in this train which is
moving with absolute uniform velocity
relative to a stalled train a train that
happens to be at rest on the surface of
the Earth for example imagine the
surface of the Earth One train moving
one train standing still the laws of
juggling are exactly the
same this uh this in fact before Galileo
this was something of a surprise in fact
not a surprise people didn't understand
that they actually imagined of course
they didn't have trains to think about
but if you would have told them about
trains and moving along with a train the
average uh scientist probably would have
thought that when you throw a fall in
the air in the train you probably have
to compensate for the motion of the
Train by if the train is moving that way
you probably have to move your arm over
to the right in order to catch the ball
because the train moving will lead to
moving out from under the thrown ball of
course this is
wrong uh the laws of juggling are the
same in the stationary train and the
moving train identical exactly the
same
uh
and that was something that Galileo
realized Galileo was the first to
realize it and Newton spelled it out in
great detail in his Laws of Motion so
let's begin with gilean re Galilean
relativity like all theories of
Relativity it's a theory of
Transformations transformations of
coordinates and transformation of
phenomena from one frame of reference to
another again a frame of reference means
as I said a lattice of meter sticks with
clocks which have been synchronized and
we'll have to discuss what we mean by
synchronized but clocks which have been
synchronized at Each corner of the
lattice and now we can imagine having
two such lates one is moving relative to
the
other one is moving relative to the
other in each frame of reference the
clocks have been synchronized in the
appropriate way and so we have to
transform information from one frame of
reference to
another various kinds of information
what is the energy of an object what is
the temperature of an object uh I don't
know any number of different kinds of
quantities we could ask if you know it
in one frame of reference what is it in
the other frame of reference now the
simplest uh the simplest set of
quantities has to do with location
location in space and location in time
the things which are recorded by the
meter
sticks and the
clocks so how do we transform from one
frame of reference to another here we
have a frame of
reference uh let's first of all draw a
frame of reference the first thing to do
when you start a relativity problem is
to draw a picture and the picture is a
picture of space time time time
vertically as
always and space horizontally and at
least in the
beginning uh we're mainly going to be
interested in problems involving motion
along one particular axis so let's call
it the x- axis the Y and Z directions
for the moment will be rather passive
they won't play any great role for a
while they'll come into things and so
every point in space and time
uh or every point on the Blackboard
stands for a place in space and a time
in
time so it's called space time naturally
enough okay now let's and if if I wanted
to draw the meter sticks let's just
imagine drawing the meter sticks one
here's the origin here's the origin
right here time equals zero here the
clocks have been all adjusted so the
time is equal to zero all along the
horizontal
axis
and as we flow up the clocks tick off
time seconds years whatever it happens
to be all right now if we move down the
line a little bit we come to the end of
the first meter stick so here's the end
of the first meter stick its trajectory
is a trajectory in SpaceTime the second
meter stick is over here the third meter
stick is over over here and the sequence
of meter sticks laid out along the
horizontal axis as time goes on Define a
series of Stripes like this which
represents locations in space if you
like this is X = 0 x = 1 needless to say
we can also go backward to x = -1 x = -2
and so
forth uh there's no reason to stop at
xal 0 x = 1 x = 2 xal 3 xal 4 and so
forth now the clocks tick and so a clock
which reads is there is no time that we
call zero is there we never hear of
talking about time zero I mean you know
an ordinary clock time Z is usually what
we call 12 midnight I
guess but anyway let's use the term time
t equal 0 tal 0 was over here T = 1 one
what 1 second or what whatever 2 seconds
3 seconds 4 seconds 5 seconds and now if
we draw some horizontal lines those
represent lines of constant
time so the whole world space and time
becomes a lattice not a real lattice an
imaginary lattice and you can make that
lattice as fine as you like it doesn't
have to be meters it could be
centimeters or micro microns or plun
lengths or if smaller than that makes
any sense uh we can uh we can make it as
fine as we like and in that way every
point in SpaceTime represents a precise
time and a precise Place according to
this lattice all right now that's your
reference frame you are the people in
the station or in this or in the broke
down train which isn't moving right
you're sitting there waiting at rest at
the surface of the
Earth but my train is moving and my
train is moving with velocity V all
right I'm in the Caboose of the train at
the tail end and let's say at time T
equals
z the
Caboose is right over here but as time
moves
on as time moves ahead my train moves
forward I'll assume it moves forward it
could also move backward and so the tail
end of the
Caboose looks like
that
my the next car might look like this I'm
imagining now Cars 1 M
long and so my series of
um constant position
coordinates are tilted relative to yours
in a space-time plot like this all right
now we're not going we're not up
to Einstein yet we're doing Galileo and
Newton Galileo and Newton could ask the
question if you people in the station
give a certain set of coordinates let's
say x and t to an
event is's an event right over here an
event means a point of SpaceTime if you
label the point of space SP time x and t
in what we'll call the stationary
reference frame what are the coordinates
that I assigned to it in my moving
reference frame well if Galileo were
here he would look at this and say look
time is time I believe like Newton will
believe in a few years that time is
universal everybody agrees about time
and in fact he could sort of check that
there weren't very good watches at that
time but he could uh check it with a
pendulum or something like that and he
could take the pendulum and if he was
careful he could put the pendulum on a
moving train there were no trains there
were no watches but he could imagine
taking his pendulum and moving it along
and bringing it back and checking it
against the pendulum at rest and if he
did it well and he did it carefully he
would find that the two pendulums agreed
uh the way the pendulums move would not
in any way influence how how rapidly
they tick off and of course that's true
for the pendulums until the pendulums St
moving too fast right so Galileo first
of all would have
said t
Prime that's the time in my frame of
reference the moving reference frame is
the same as your
time but my coordinate X
Prime what does my coordinate mean let's
take this point over here the coordinate
the x coordinate that I assigned to this
point over here is the distance not to
your origin of coordinates not to your
origin of space but to my origin of
space my origin of space is over
here okay so I will assign a smaller x x
Prime will be small smaller than x and
what it will be will be X your
x minus the amount that you move or
sorry the amount that I move in time T
and that's going to be minus the
velocity time
T So T Prime equal t x Prime is equal to
xus VT where V is the relative velocity
of the two frames of
reference okay uh we can go back and
forth we
can solve we could solve this equation
this gives me the primed coordinates in
terms of the
unprimed I could solve this and rewrite
it as t equal T
Prime x = x Prime + V now I I would if I
just use the second equation I would
write plus VT
but since T is the same as T Prime I'll
just write VT Prime here the top
equation would be how the moving would
be how uh the stationary Observer
converts his information into the
information of a moving Observer and the
inverse equation would be how you go
back okay this is the basic mathematics
of Galilean
relativity okay let's check some things
first of all what kind of things are
invariant the idea of invariance is very
important the idea of
invariant or in or an
invariant invariant is both an adjective
and a
noun uh equations can be
invariant an invariant means a thing
which everybody agrees about a quantity
that everybody agrees about all right so
let me give you an example of a quantity
that everybody agrees about everybody
meaning these two observers or any other
ones that we also throw in Yeah question
um you were saying about the pendulum
how you can check yes that you can take
pendulum well I I was I was uh yeah and
come back yeah um how does he know that
um when move the pendulum
away he's speeding it up then
it's kind
ofer of course the answer is he
doesn't but if you do it with an
ordinary
watch with a good no I mean we have
Galileo would have known it I think
Galileo just guessed it how you would do
it is you would take your highquality
Rolex
watch and you would just go and do it
one person would stay in a seat and the
other person would March around the room
a few hundred times and then come back
and check their
watches
now the answer of course that we know
because of hindsight and because we're
living in the 21st century and Einstein
was 100 years ago is there will be a
tiny discrepancy but that discrepancy is
so
small that uh for ordinary purposes for
ordinary daily
experience we would simply say
the rate at which clocks tick off time
doesn't depend on the motion and that's
an experimental fact experimental fact
in the sense that uh that if we actually
did it with ordinary clocks it would
work it would work to very high
Precision of course at some level it
fails but that's what special relativity
is
about I guess ignoring the special
relativity thing I just have a problem
that you're bringing the clock back to
the same spot yeah
that's
whatever oh you think it might have sped
up as your one way and
uh yeah well that might have happened uh
that would mean that there was basically
a difference between left motion and
right motion so we could try the same
experiment going the other way well
maybe the same thing would happen but
then we could we if East and West we
would try it North and South we might
also take my watch and go around you in
circles for a long period of time and do
all kinds kind of experiments or just go
One Direction and use a telescope
use all kinds of all kinds of ways we
try all sorts of obvious things and they
all work and they all work right um
don't need a telescope use a telephone
to to communicate the information back
and
forth uh send light signals back and
forth to check our watches and so forth
and it would work very well
it will work very well until we start to
move too fast okay then we then then it
breaks down all right but the point is
that Galilean relativity was based on a
guess it was frankly based on a guess
and the mathematical translation of the
guess is these equations right now there
are some obvious
invariants for example here's something
that's
invariant at an instant of time look at
the distance
between two events two events which are
synchronous or simultaneous simultaneous
being used to mean at the same time take
two events at the same
time the distance between
them will be
invariant why is that let's take the two
events let's take the two events let's
call them
X1 at time T1 and X2 at also at the same
time T let's not even bother labeling
the time at the same
time these are two events at the same
time and the distance between them is
simply X2 - X1 and that we can call
distance right what about the primed
coordinates the primed coordinates our X
Prime 1 is equal to X1 minus VT
X Prime 2 is X2 minus
VT notice that the actual coordinates
are not
invariant they don't assign the same
values of X but they do assign the same
values if we now subtract these two or
subtract them the bottom one the top one
from the bottom one then X Prime 2 - x
Prime
1 is equal to X2 - X1 one and then the
VTS
cancel so the separation between two
points at the same instant of time I
emphasize at the same instant of time
because it wouldn't be true if we did it
at different instance of time yeah the
t's on the right yeah are not the same
as the t's on the left yeah they
are with an event at
x1t and another event at x2t T this is T
over here right okay got it got it okay
this is T is x
2 here's
X1 right the separation between the two
points is an
invariant that's the language we would
use uh let's imagine that we have a
particle trajectory a particle
trajectory means an X of t
X as a function of T would be a
trajectory of some particle I'll put it
over here trajectory of some particle is
an X at each function of time first of
all is the position invariant no x and x
Prime are not the same thing but we can
write X Prime of
T is equal to X of
T minus
VT all right so if I know if I know the
trajectory X of T not V of T but V *
T if I know the trajectory of a particle
or if you know the trajectory of a
particle X of T you can communicate it
to me and the communication will be in
the form of telling me what x Prime of T
is what I will see is an X Prime of T
which will be your X of T minus
VT all right so the coordinate of the
part particle itself is not invariant
what about the velocity the velocity is
just the time derivative of the position
all right so the velocity which would
just be let's call it DX Prime by
DT that's equal to DX by
DT minus V so no velocities are not
invariant what you see is the velocity I
see the velocity being
diminished V could of course be negative
I mean there's nothing uh intrinsic
about the sign of
V but um I see a velocity which is
shifted by amount V that's obvious of
course I'm moving along you shoot an
arrow I see the arrow going slower than
you see the arrow going for obvious
reasons what about acceleration so so
first of all position and velocity are
not relativistic in variance in
Galileo's theory of relativity but let's
differentiate again to get the
acceleration DC X Prime well let's see
by let's let's put it here DC X Prime by
DT ^2 that's the acceleration that I
see is equal to the acceleration that
you see
minus the time derivative of V but V is
a constant I am
assuming that the relative velocity
between the two frames of reference is
constant that's equivalent to saying
that these tilted lines are straight
lines so the
acceleration the difference V doesn't
make any difference the time derivative
of a constant is zero and so
acceleration is an invariant the
acceleration that I see of an object I
mean not my acceleration I'm not
accelerating I'm in the Caboose of the
train I'm moving along with uniform
velocity but I see objects moving back
and forth in front of me moving to the
left moving to the right uh sometimes
they
accelerate you see the same objects you
also see them accelerate and we will
agree age about the acceleration so
acceleration is an
invariant
now I I shouldn't I'm not sure I I'm not
sure which is cause and effect here
really but let's uh say it this way the
fact that acceleration is itself an
invariant as a strong suggestion that
the laws of physics should be in terms
of
acceleration not velocity not position
that the law of phys physics the laws of
motion if they are to be
invariant if they are to be invariant
the laws of physics should involve
acceleration since we all agree on the
acceleration well of course that's
exactly what FAL ma
says force is equal to mass time
acceleration acceleration we all agree
about acceleration well let's analyze
this a little more closely suppose we're
talking about two objects which exert
forces on each other and for the moment
everything is taking place along the
x-axis we we usually imagine correctly
for most cases that the force between
two objects only depends on the distance
between them right only depends on the
distance between them the force between
two
objects gravitational force
electrostatic force only depends on the
distance between them the coordinates of
the particles themselves are not
invariant but the distance between them
is
invariant
that's what we well where did we write
it up on the top here everybody agrees
about the distance so the distance is an
invariant and if the force only depends
on the distance it says that the force
between two objects is in invariant
meaning to say that everybody agrees
about it
so if you in your frame were to measure
the force between these two objects
which are moving somehow and I in my
frame whizzing by it measure the force
according to Newton and
Galileo and everybody who came after
them up to Einstein force is a
invariant because the distance between
two objects is invariant
that leaves only one more symbol in this
equation
mass in order for Newton's Theory to
make any sense it was necessary that
mass is an
invariant if all the terms in the
equation are invariant then so must be
the mass and so according to
Newton every object has a mass and
everybody agrees about that mass there's
no discrepancy because an object is
moving
uh about a 1 kilog object there a 1
kilog object there a 1 kilog object even
if it's moving past you on a railroad
train so Newton's law of
motion is invariant here's the language
Newton's law of motion is invariant
under
Galilean coordinate Transformations
there a Galilean coordinate
transformation and Newton's Laws of
Motion are invariant under it
the idea of Relativity is that all the
laws of nature whatever they happen to
be are invariant under the appropriate
analog
of of Galilean uh of the Galilean
transformation now the problem is that
that clashed with
electromagnetism at the moment we
haven't learned anything about
electromagnet
ISM but you all know that
electromagnetic waves are called light
and that light moves with a certain
velocity Maxwell's equations predict
what that velocity is and if you think
of Maxwell's
equations as laws of physics that
everybody should agree
on then the speed of light must be the
same for
everybody that's really all there was to
it Einstein really used no more than
that course he was guessing he was
guessing that Maxwell's equations were
the same in every reference frame in
other words he was guessing that
Maxwell's equations which were were laws
of nature which were so compelling that
they would have to be the same in every
reference frame and that of course led
to a big problem it led to the problem
of the speed of
light that if Maxwell's equations are
the same in all reference
frames then the speed of light is the
same in all reference frames but how can
the speed of light be the same in all
reference frames uh if one frame is
moving relative to the other we could
work it out we could work it out using
Galilean
relativity uh let's uh let's take a
light Ray a light
Ray a little blip a little blip of a
light Ray moving along it moves along
with x equals C * T that's what where C
is the speed of light okay um that's
what Maxwell's equations
said
well Galileo would then have had to say
let's ask how that light Ray appears to
move from the point of view of the
moving reference frame and that will
be X
Prime which is equal to xus
VT
so far this is just the just the
Galilean representation of the
transformation that is equal to
CT X is equal to CT minus
VT and he would have just said well
that's the same thing as saying C minus
V
T So Galileo would have had no choice
but to say in the moving reference frame
the speed of of light differs from the
speed of light in the stationary
reference frame by the relative
velocity uh that of course make good
intuitive sense it is the way sound
would work it is the way water waves
would
work if water waves move what's a what's
a typical velocity of a water wave I
don't know uh couple of meters a second
or something like
that how much few for small on yeah yeah
yeah yeah meters per second let's say 1
meter per second but I'm flying over at
a half a meter per second I'm flying
over the wave then I see the wave moving
at a half a meter per second so it's
completely unreasonable to uh to expect
that water waves have a universal
velocity that all observers see now most
physicists of course at the turn of the
or at the end of the 19th century simply
came to the conclusion
that well in the 1850s 1860s when
Maxwell was was active simply came to
the conclusion that some frames of
reference are better than other frames
of reference that there is no
relativity uh that there exists a frame
of reference God's frame of
reference don't tell the UDS men I said
that or do tell you I'm
budsman God's frame of reference where
Maxwell's equations are correct in other
frames of reference Maxwell's equations
must be somewhat different because in
other frames of reference obviously
light moves with different
velocity and so as you well
know various physicists tried to study
the dependence of the velocity of light
on the state of motion of an observer
and system atically they found no
dependence we won't go through the
various
experiments uh several different kinds
of experiments to try to detect the fact
that a moving Observer would see a speed
of light which would depend on the state
of motion and as you know no such effect
was ever
discovered
uh the result being that physicists had
no choice but to go and review the basic
uh ideas that went into this definition
now Einstein himself claimed he never
even knew about the experiments I'm
inclined to believe him I mean you know
they didn't call Einstein Einstein for
nothing I mean he
he so I think we give him
credit he said when he was 16 years old
he thought about moving along with a
light wave the light wave didn't didn't
oscillate didn't move didn't do anything
anything just looked Frozen and he
somehow knew enough to know that
Maxwell's equations uh were inconsistent
with that and his choice was to believe
that Maxwell's equations were basic laws
of nature basic laws of nature which
should be the same in every reference
frame so something was wrong and he had
to go back to some very very first
principles in fact the very first
principles which this
lattice
represents the idea of coordinates the
idea of times the distinct times and so
forth and went back and said let me
begin all over again with one assumption
well two assumptions the first
assumption is the principle of
Relativity namely that in every frame of
reference the laws of physics are
identical the second assumption
is that in every frame of reference the
speed of light is always the same let me
take those as postulates and see what I
can
derive the first thing he
derived was something that is implicit
in this
diagram which I partly spelled out
partly didn't spell out but let me spell
it out
now that if two events are
simultaneous as seen in one reference
frame they will be simultaneous in every
reference frame it's exactly the
statement that t Prime equals T if two
events occur at the same time in one
reference frame they occur at the same
time in any reference frame Einstein
realized very quickly that he could not
maintain that and here's here's here's
roughly the way he thought about it he
said let's let's go way back to the
beginning and even start with the whole
idea of synchronizing
clocks we can lay out our meter sticks
it's clear enough what we can do we can
lay out our meter sticks all right we
lay out our meter sticks on the ground
but now you have your clock you have
your clock you have your clock you have
your clock over there and you want to
synchronize your clocks make sure they
all read the same at the same instant of
time what does that mean well there's
various ways you could try to check
whether your clocks were were
synchronized but I Einstein decided to
use light he wanted to use light for the
obvious reason that his basic postulate
was about light so he wanted to use
light to synchronize clocks so here's
here's the way he uh synchronized clocks
he said let's see put somebody in the
middle now what does the middle mean
let's take you and you you are the two
end points what does it mean to say
somebody in the middle well you can
measure with meter sticks the person in
the middle
and adjust with the meter sticks until
that person in the middle is exactly
halfway between
you now at exactly noon you're going to
emit a flash bulb you're going to you
light up a flash bulb uh and the light
signal is going to go well it can go out
all around you but in particular it's
going to go from uh from your position
out in that direction you'll do exactly
the same thing when your clock is also
at time t equal
z uh t equal Z did I say zero or noon
whatever at at noon you will also send
out a flash signal if the person who is
in the middle sees the flashes
simultaneously other words if the left
Flash and the right flash go right by
them
simultaneously then we will agree that
your clocks are synchronized if he sees
your light your flash before your flash
then he says your you you better
readjust your clock a little bit go back
try it again set your clock back a
little bit and keep doing it
until the person in the
middle uh sees the flashes of light
instantaneously the same now everybody
in the room does the same thing with
respect to everybody else until
everybody's clocks are
synchronized uh by the Same by exactly
the same definition that somebody
halfway between
them uh uh we'll see flashes of light
emitted at the same at the same time
we'll see those flashes of light at the
same time okay then Einstein realized
there's a problem that that much is okay
that much is okay we can synchronize all
of your clocks but now what about me
moving past
you or you know let's uh let's have me
you and let's see how this should work
I have my coordinate frame laid
out and
um I move past you I look at your light
Ray I look at your light Ray but because
I'm moving by the time your light Ray
gets to me it has had to go further than
your light Ray did so it's quite obvious
that I'm going to see your light Ray
before I see your light Ray even if you
aditt them at exactly the same time even
if you admitted them at exactly the same
time according to all of your Reckoning
I who happen to be moving this way will
reckon your light Ray as being
emitted later because I see it later
because it has a greater distance to go
so Einstein realized that the idea of
simultaneity was a relative idea that if
everybody synchronized es their Clocks
by the means of light by means of light
there will be a discrepancy in what in
different frames of reference is counted
as uh as simultaneous I want to work
that out I want to work that out in
detail just using
light how does simultane how does
simultaneity break down another way to
ask it is if these two points are
counted in the stationary reference
frame as having the same
time which two points in the moving
reference frame will be said to have
exactly the same time that's something I
want to work out next we'll take five
minutes and work that out in detail and
that'll give us the lorence
Transformations Lorent Transformations
which implicitly have in them that
simultaneity is a relative concept so
that will be our next challenge to
replace this equation
by one that's consistent with the idea
that light travels with the same
velocity in all frames what if I
synchronize using sound using what sound
I just
yell then you will find then you will
find that the law that says that the
speed of sound is uh what is it about
1,00 ft per second that that's not a law
at all and that moving Observers do
detect different velocities of
[Music]
sound you if you do it at rest in a
frame of reference where the air is at
rest that's a perfectly good way to
synchronize uh to synchronize clocks but
then somebody moving
uh you'll do all these things and you'll
discover in the end that it's not
consistent to say that the speed of
sound is the same in every reference
frame
what what we're going to be using we're
going to use the idea that light is the
same there's nothing wrong with
synchronizing clocks that way nothing at
all uh you wouldn't want to do it though
you wouldn't want to synchronize clocks
on a moving
train if the train was an open air train
and the and you get the point if it was
an open air train and the atmosphere was
at rest and you were moving through the
atmosphere that would be a bad way to
synchronize uh to synchronize your your
clock your clocks H this would be like
having yeah yeah yeah exactly exactly so
Einstein said he doesn't care he is
going to Simply assume the speed of
light is the same and see where it takes
him uh see where it leads does it lead
to something consistent all right so as
I said his first observation was there's
something wrong with the idea that
simultaneity is universal or that the
simultaneity of two events is an
invariant so here's how we began here's
I I actually don't know how we be this
is the way I
begin
um it's been too long since I've read
his paper let's again we begin with a
drawing and now we have two this is the
rest
frame and we have
two
points laid out a distance L
apart this distance is L and this
distance is l l stands for length now it
could be 1 meter but let's keep it
General a distance L is measured off
another distance L is measured off and
here
are the
trajectories of the points which
correspond to uh uh to being L units
apart okay this could be your seat and
that could be your seat and the one in
the middle since it's equally distant
between the two of them is the person
who happens to be vacant but is sitting
in the middle between the two of
you okay so that's that's the first
setup now
now if the clocks are synchronized what
does that mean exactly it means that if
at time T equals z
both observers at the two ends here send
out a light signal the light signal the
light signals will
intersect at the same place like
this oops I missed that a light signal
from this side if it's sent out at the
same instant in other words synchronous
in this frame of reference the light
signal is sent out from this instant
that the two light signals will cross
the intermediate Observer here at
exactly the same
time now light moves of course very fast
that means that this drawing is a bit um
well that's a little funny because light
moving so fast it would mean that light
rays are practically horizontal they
move an enormous distance in a short
amount of time but we can fix that we
can fix that by working in units in
which the speed of light is equal to one
let's do that later on we'll put back
the speed of light but for the moment
let's set the speed of light equal to
one how do you do that you work in units
of space which are adjusted the right
way so that in one second of
time uh light goes one unit of distance
light a light second or years in light
years or whatever uh whatever you like
and so the vertical axis and the
horizontal axis here are measured in
units in which the speed of light is
equal to one if the speed of light is
equal to one then a light Ray satisfies
xal
T not CT but just
T and that would be a 45° line that's a
light Ray moving to the right a light
Ray moving to the right
satisfies a light R moving to the right
from the origin over
here satisfies xal T what if it's a
light Ray moving to the right from some
other
position well then it
satisfies
x equal t plus some
constant namely the offset so if it's a
light Ray any light Ray moving to the
right satisfies X Al t plus
something
what thank you D now what about a light
R moving to the
left that's
x equal minus t or minus t plus some
other constant plus d Prime I don't know
so these are these are the Motions of
light rays and they correspond to 45°
angles 45° angles a slope of one a slope
of one corresponds to a velocity of the
speed of light things moving slower than
the speed of
light move ver move more toward the
vertical if it made sense to think about
things moving faster than the speed of
light which it doesn't they would be
moving on trajectories which were more
horizontal
so these two these two clocks are
synchronized
because if at the same instant of time
or another way of saying it is these two
points here must be at the same instant
of time in this reference frame in the
stationary reference frame because the
light rays will intersect the
intermediate Observer here right at the
same instant of time now let's draw in a
second Observer the second observer in
other words a second reference frame and
the second reference frame is moving
moving it's supposed to be a straight
line and it's moving with a motion X =
VT V is now the velocity of the moving
Observer and this curve here is now x
equal VT from my or from your
perspective I'm moving along with
velocity
V so you watch me and you say at each
instant of time my position moves and it
moves with a velocity V this is
incidentally the definition of
velocity this is the definition of the
Velocity that you see me move with okay
so this is moving along like here let's
draw in some more lines here's the
here's a second I want to draw this
Gooden parallel to the
first
does that look parallel close close
enough this one's also pretty
parallel like
that
okay what do we want to do
[Applause]
next
ah okay now let's look at the moving
frame of reference
again this this guy is halfway between
these
two right he started out over here
halfway between these two they're moving
with uniform velocity he stays halfway
between these two but notice that at his
location the two light rays do not
arrive at his position at the same time
at his location one of the light rays
arrives much later than the other one
so according to this moving Observer he
must conclude that these two points were
not
synchronous the light rays emitted from
here and here could not have been
synchronous from his point of view
because from his point of view they
should have arrived at his at the
intermediate position at the same time
in fact he can reverse the logic he can
say where along this light
Ray does it correspond let's see how do
I say this right yeah
um let's forget this light Ray for a
minute and let's follow this one until
it actually
hits the
Observer this is the person in the
Middle where would a light Ray have to
come
from along this trajectory in order that
the guy in the middle here would
conclude that the two light rays were
emitted
simultaneously it's easy just trace a
backward light Ray also at 45° to that
point trace a light Ray backward along
45° to a point over here and now in the
moving frame of reference if a light Ray
is emitted over here and a light Ray is
emitted over here this is a bit of an
exaggeration ation I think this line is
too uh too
shallow it go back a little
more hit exactly the same
place
yeah if a light R were emitted from here
to the left and a light R were emitted
from here to the right they would hit
the central Observer over here at
exactly the same time so the moving
Observer will conclude that this point
and this point are synchronous whereas
the stationary Observer
concludes that this point and this point
are synchronous it's obvious from the
beginning that the idea of synchronous
cannot be the same in the two frames but
can we do it quantitatively can we
really figure out
quantitatively exactly where this point
lies and can we figure out all the
points
that the moving Observer will call
synchronous with the origin over here
and that's not too hard it just requires
a little bit of simple algebra so a
little bit of geometry and algebra let's
work it
out the first thing to
do the first thing to do is to make some
simple equations for all the lines that
are drawn here right we need some simple
we want to be quantitative I want to
write some equations for the various
lines this line is xal VT what is this
line over here this line is X let's
write it in
X =
VT plus
L why because it's shifted over by
distance
l so for its X is VT plus L this is X
means from the stationary reference
frame the stationary reference frame
sees the black lines shifted up by
distance l so it's X = VT + L what about
this
one VT + 2
L that's xal VT + 2 L we want to locate
this point the object is to locate this
point right over here why because it's
the one that the moving Observer says is
synchronous with the origin so we' like
to find out where it is what's the
equation for this line
xal
T that equation is xal T let's first
locate this point this point is at the
intersection of two lines that we know
one of them is x = t and the other is X
= VT + L let's write those two equations
and find out where those two lines
intersect so one of them is just xal
T and the other one is X = VT + L all
right that's easy wherever you see X put
T and we get
T =
VT + L or 1 - V * t =
l one more step t equal L / 1us V do I
have that
right let's check
yes that's this point right over here it
occurs in the rest frame at a
time which is V which is L / 1 minus V
what about x what about the x of that
point it's equal to T all along this
line the same
thing x = l/ 1 -
V that's this point over here let's call
it Point capital
A this is point capital
A now now that we know where Point
capital A
is let's see if we can trace a line
backward until it hits here and figure
out where this point is that's our goal
to find out where this point is all
right what about this line what do we
know about this line we know about this
line that it's a backward goinging light
Ray so it's of the form xus T is equal
to a constant oh sorry xal minus t plus
a constant the backward going light Ray
is x = minus t plus
something let me just give that
something I don't want to call it D
Prime I'm going to call it b or another
way to write it is that x + t equal B we
don't know what B is yet how am I going
to find B this is x + t = b how will I
find B anybody got an idea yeah
it's it's the same
it's
right right what we do is we use the
fact that this line goes through this
point right this
line goes through this point at this
point x and t are equal and what are
they equal to they're equal to l over
1us V so at this point over here x + T
is just twice L / 1us V and that's equal
to B so we found B we found out what
the this B is that goes into this
equation for this back W moving light
Ray over here right let's write it down
x +
T is equal to 2
L / 1us
V so now I know this
line but I want to find its intersection
with this one so I'll write right
underneath this equation I'll write the
equation for this line that's X = BT + 2
L all right I now have two
equations that tell me where the
intersection point is let's see should
we solve
them a little bit of a nuisance to solve
them but let's do
it uh okay no it's not hard at
all let's subtract the two equations
that will get rid of X for us if I
subtract the two equations that will get
rid of X that'll give me on the left
here
T and on the right hand side I will have
equals 2 L over 1us
V
minus looks
like am I doing this right
minus
VT minus 2
L oh no plus 2 L no minus 2
L minus 2
L all right let's move all the T stuff
over to the left that gives us T * 1 -
V
equal
1 plus v equal 2 L both these terms have
2 L in them and then one of them has 1
over 1 - V and the other one just has
minus1 right 2 L is common to both of
them it's out here and it's just L over
oh sorry it's just 1 over 1us V -
1 okay what's 1 over 1 - V
-1 uh uh it's just V over one just V
over 1 minus V yeah
right yeah 1 over 1-
vus 1 - V over 1 - V is 1 - 1 cancels V
over 1 - V right V over 1 minus
V and finally I have now located what T
is T is 2
L time V
/ 1 - V * 1 +
V 1 - V * 1 + V is just 1 - v^ 2 so
first of all I found T is equal to 2 l v
over 1 - V ^
2 that's the time of this point over
here T what about its X well that's easy
to find we can find it from two ways we
can either find it by plugging into this
line or by plugging into this
line which one uh is simpler let's see
uh it looks to me like it's easier to
plug into this
one okay so let's plug into this one
that says that X is equal to 2 L / 1 - V
minus
t minus 2 2
LV over 1 - V ^
2 anybody do that in their head no you
no I think we better do it we better
multiply top and bottom by 1 plus v so
that we have the same Den we have the
same denominator so let's multiply by 1
plus well let's do it separately 2 L * 1
+
V
/ 1 - V ^
2us 2 l
v it looks like to me like it's just 2 L
/ 1us V ^
2 right so it's
x = 2
l/ 1 - V
^2 now I'm actually not so interested in
either t or x what I'm interested in is
the slope of this
line I'm interested in the slope of this
line which is the
ratio of theta
X I'm actually interested in what this
line is I'm interested in this curve
here this curve has the form x equals
something time T but we can read off
what it is now it's just the ratio of x
to T what's the ratio of x to T the
ratio of x to T is just V
is just V so this curve is tal
VX let's check that t = VX yes T has an
extra factor of v in it from x t = v *
X well that's kind of
interesting
we did this whole big
construction and what we found out is
that with the moving Observer calls
synchronous the stationary Observer
calls tal
VX we can erase everything
else let's just keep track here's the
moving Observer he moves with xal
VT that's his X that's his time axis xal
VT but the x axis is tal VX
okay all these points along here are at
the same position from the point of view
of the moving Observer all these points
along here are at the same time from the
point of view of the moving Observer all
these points are synchronous from the
moving observer's point of view not from
the stationary point of view and look
one of them says x equals VT the other
says tal VX very symmetrically related
to each
other very symmetrically related let's
just abstract from the whole thing now
what we've learned because we've set c
equal to
1 okay so let's actually put some units
into it let's get the units
right when you do a thing like you set c
equal to
one then of
course lengths and times have exactly
the same units and velocities are
dimensionless the velocity is the ratio
of a length to a time if C is one
velocities are are dimensionless but
let's try to get some Dimensions back
into it and restore some uh correct
Dimensions to it all we have to do is
multiply by the appropriate powers of
the speed of light in order to get the
dimensions to be
consistent this is already consistent X
is equal to a velocity which is a length
over time times a time but this one does
not look consistent what do we have to
do to it to make it consistent the
answer is I think divid it by the square
of the speed of light when the speed of
light is set equal to 1 this curve is
tal VX there's a unique way to restore
the C's so that you get the same answer
when C is equal to one but so that
dimensions are restored let's check the
dimensions this is a time we have a time
equals now a velocity is a length over a
Time and X is a length and in the
denominator we have a length squared
over a Time squared so let's see that is
that is in fact dimensionally correct
yeah a c in the denominator a c squ in
the denominator restores the dimensions
so if we include the speed of light that
would be the formula in fact including
the speed of light you see something
interesting you see that when the speed
of light is very very large the slope of
of this line is very very small t equal
V * X ided by an enormously big
number speed of light uh squared in
metric units is 10 to the 17th or
something so this is an enormously big
number downstairs and that says that
this is a very very shallow line so
shallow that uh for most practical
purposes simultaneity really is the same
in reference
frames but when things are moving with
anything like the speed of light we have
to account for uh for these
discrepancies and
so but if we set the speed of light
equal to one then the diagram has a
lovely symmetry the slope of this
line relative to the horizontal is the
same as the slope of this line relative
to the
vertical so let's let's redraw it let's
just abstract out of it we have your
coordinates x and t and we have my
coordinates uh T Prime and X
prime a light signal let's put a light
signal in there a light signal moving to
the right is at
45° and a light signal moving to the
left is at uh
135° so you see what's happened
the
the new coordinates are sort of
symmetric relative to the light Ray here
but the
surface which is the surface of
simultaneity let's give it a name this
is the surface of simultaneity in the in
the moving reference
frame set of points that the moving
Observer says are all at the same time
are tilted relative to the surface of
simultaneity in the rest frame and
they're tilted exactly the same
way that uh that the
axis that the time axis is tilted so
it's a very simple
construction now from this
construction we can make some guesses
not guesses we can actually derive the
form of the Lorent
Transformations Let's uh let's work
out the luren transformation
we know a good deal about the relation
between XT and X Prime and T Prime we
know a good deal but we don't know
everything so we need some more we need
some more
input let's uh go back to Galileo
Galileo said X Prime is equal to xus
VT all this says all this says is that
when X is equal to VT X Prime is equal
to zero but that's should be true that
should continue to be true it should be
continue to be true that as far as
you're
concerned my position satisfies x equal
VT so when X is equal to VT you're
talking about my origin of coordinates
so it must still be true not that X
Prime is equal to x - V T but that when
X is equal to VT X Prime must be
zero my center of coordinates is what
you call xal VT that continues to be
true that's just a statement that this
line is xal
VT and this line of course is also X
Prime equal 0 it's also X Prime equal
zero it's the center of coordinates of
the moving primed Observer so
this equation may be
wrong but it must be correct that when
xal VT X Prime is equal to Z how could
this be wrong but still be true that
when X is equal to VT X Prime is equal
to Z there's only one way that there
could be some factor in here let's call
it
f and that factor could depend on
velocity that's a
possibility this is still consistent
with the statement that when X X is
equal to VT X Prime is equal to Z but
it's not quite the same as saying X
Prime is equal to x - VT it's a little
different than what Galilea would have
written depending on what F of V is
here
so um this is about all you can do with
the equation with Galileo's first
equation that still allows X Prime to be
zero when X is equal to VT to have some
numerical multiple there and that
numeric multiple could in principle
depend on the
velocity
right
uh and as I said all this is telling us
here is that xal VT is the same as X
Prime equal
0 now let's look at this second curve
the second curve over here is T Prime
equals
z why is it t Prime equals z because all
along this curve here
the primed Observer the moving Observer
says that the time is the
same right if we just choose it at this
point to be zero here then T Prime is
equal to zero all along this curve so
what it
says whatever the equation for T Prime
is it must have the form T minus
VX possibly times some other function of
velocity what does this mean what why am
I saying this all this says is that when
tal
VX that's this curve T Prime is equal to
zero when T equals VX T Prime is equal
to
zero this is about all that you could
have and still be consistent with saying
that this is the axis X Prime equal 0
and this is the axis T Prime is equal to
zero so Einstein wrote this
down but one more step this is not quite
enough because we don't know what this F
and this G are they could be
anything they could be anything these
two equations here tell us about the
tilt of these axes but they don't tell
us what f and g are we need one more
step I'll tell you what the one more
step
is the one more step is is that whatever
the equations that you
use to convey to me information should
be essentially exactly the same as the
equations I would use to convey
information back to you with one
exception the sign of the
Velocity the sign of the Velocity in
other
words in other words if we were to solve
these equations for x and t in terms of
X Prime and T Prime the equation should
have exactly the same form except the
sign of the Velocity should change so
let's do that let's solve these
equations uh
for x and t in terms of X Prime and T
Prime this is the inverse relation if
this is what the moving coordinates are
in terms of the stationary coordinates
then if we solve it for x and t we'll
know what the stationary coordinates are
in terms of the moving coordinates and
the pattern should be essentially
exactly the
same right if you see me moving with
velocity V then I see you moving in the
opposite direction with velocity V and
the only difference in the in the
relationship would be the sign of the
Velocity all right so I'm going to solve
these equations let's see this is a
nuisance it's very straightforward but
let's do it
anyway
uh
ah no let's prove something first let's
first prove that f and g have to be the
same why do f and g have to be the same
that is the statement that everybody
agrees about the speed of
light in other
words if one Observer calls this line x
=
t the other Observer must call it X
Prime = T Prim
if one Observer says the speed of light
is one that means xal T the other
Observer must also say that the speed of
light is one that was Einstein's basic
principle that we all agree about the
speed of
light if a light Ray satisfies xal T it
must also satisfy X Prime equal T Prime
let's see if we can see what that
says if x = T along a light
Ray then X Prime here is just equal to T
* 1 - V over F of
V I've just used that X is equal to T on
the other hand T
Prime is equal to T * 1 - V over G of
V I've again just used that X is equal
to T along the light R so along the
light ray x Prime is given by this T
Prime is given by this but it must also
be true that X Prime must equal T prime
otherwise the speed of light would not
be the same in the two
frames well if x Prime is must be equal
to T prime it means f and g have to be
the same
function no choice about it so
Einstein's assumption that the speed of
light is the same in all reference
frames
required that f and g are the
same so we've learned a little
more again we've used the idea of
simultaneity as being defined by light
rays coming from the left and the right
and hooking up at the same instant of
time for The Observer halfway in between
that told us
what this curve was all right and now
we've used the statement that the speed
of light is the same in all reference
frames in other words if x equals T
along here then X Prime must equal T
Prime and that tells us that this
function is the same as this function
not quite everything we need to know we
still don't know what F of V
is f of v in the denominator
good
and F is just some unknown function of v
that maybe we'll find some reason to set
equal to something
particular there must be some rule which
tells us what it is all right let's now
solve for x and t in terms of X Prime
and T
Prime let's just solve these
relationships
uh okay let's
just let's do
it let me multiply this by F of v f of V
* X Prime is equal to x -
VT and F of V * T Prime is equal to T
minus
VX all right let's see what's uh what
should we do with these
to I want to solve for x X in terms of
the Prime variables so let's solve for x
in terms of the Prime variables and the
best way to do that is to divide this
equation by V
uh let's see
uh v no let's multiply this equation by
V
here why did I do that I did that so
that if I just subtract them I'll get
rid of the VT and I'll have an equation
for x
okay let's see what it says um just add
them add them so I get x * 1 - V ^2 on
the
right the VTS cancel and that's equal
to
um f of v x
prime plus v f of V
T
Prime let let me just uh write that a
little nicer F of
V times I think it was just
um X XE VT X prime plus VT
Prime and now divide it by 1-
v^2
that's the equation for x there's
another equation for T which is very
similar the equation for T looks very
similar it looks like f of V / 1 - V ^ 2
time T Prime + v x
Prime that's the inverse relationship if
you go from X to t x to X Prime one set
of equations then the way that you go
back is with the this set of equations
well you would expect if there is nice
symmetry between the two frames of
reference that the two sets of equations
should look very parallel to each other
in fact x and t should be related to X
Prime and T Prime in exactly the same
way that X Prime and t t Prime are
related to x and t with one exception
with the perception that the sign of the
Velocity should be
opposite well that doesn't look so bad
here we have X Prime is x - VT *
something here we have X is equal to X
Prime + VT Prime Times something if the
somethings were the same if F of V over
1 - V ^ 2 were the same as 1 / V the
relationship would be completely
reciprocal the relationship would be
completely reciprocal same here the
relation between the primed and unprimed
variables when you invert it simply
involves changing the sign of the
Velocity from T minus vx to T prime plus
VX that will be true
if F of V / 1us v^ 2 is the same as 1/ F
of
V
so far I haven't told you what F of V is
now I'm telling you it's the thing which
satisfies this equation or another way
to write it is that F of
V is equal to the square root of 1us V
^2 multiply by F of v on both sides that
squares this multiply by 1 - v^ 2 1 - v^
2 and take the the square
root what was this what did I do what I
did was simply to make sure that the
relation between the primed and the
unprimed coordinates were
reciprocal that if the unprimed Observer
tells the primed
Observer that his coordinates are
related that the coordinates are related
in a certain way the inverse
relationship should be of exactly the
same form except with the velocity
having the opposite sign all that says
is if you see me move with velocity V I
see you move with velocity minus
V so now we have the complete set of
relationships between the coordinates of
a point of space time in one frame and
the coordinates in another frame and
here they are X Prime is equal to x - VT
/ < TK of 1 - v^ 2 and T Prime is equal
to t -
VX over < TK 1 - V ^
2 we can solve them I just did it but
let me write down what the solution is
solving it meaning to relate to write
the equations for T and X instead of X
Prime and T Prime the inverse relations
are X is equal to X Prime + VT Prime / <
TK of 1 - V ^2 and T is equal to T Prime
+ VX Prime over < TK of 1 - V ^
2 why does one have a plus v and the
other have a minus V for exactly the
reasons that I said one velocity is the
opposite of the other you see me with
one velocity I see you with the other
velocity
these are the relationships between the
coordinates of two reference frames
which ensure that everybody see the same
velocity of light that light has the
same velocity to
everybody and that the relationships
between coordinates are
reciprocal you everybody know what I
mean by reciprocal that they have the
same form no matter which way you go
from one side to the other and they're
quite unique that's uh that's it and the
new thing here the new bizarre thing is
that time is not just time that what's
synchronous in one frame of reference in
other words T equals a constant is not
the same as T Prime equals a constant
that's this the new thing that
synchronicity is not the same in both
reference frames now I've left out the
speed of light by now I should put back
the speed of
light c not equal to one and all we have
to do then is to um put C in to make the
equations have dimensional consistency X
and VT have the same dimensions and in
fact they have the same dimensions as X
Prime X Prime X and VT all have the same
dimensions well the only thing that's
out of Kila here is that velocity does
not have the same dimensions as one you
cannot subtract the thing with one set
of Dimensions from a thing with another
set of Dimensions one has no Dimensions
it's dimensionless velocity is length
over time all we have to do to fix this
is divide V ^2 by
c^2 1 minus v^2 over c^
2 if C is set equal to one then it just
reproduces the original answer if C is
not equal to one it's dimensionally
consistent what about this equation here
though this one is a little bit tougher
uh T and VX do not have the same units T
Prime and T have the same units but VX
does not have the units of time we have
to divide this by the square of the
speed of light c^ s and again put c^ s
down
here so it's T minus v/ c^2
X
ided < TK of 1 - v^2 over
c^2 now it's interesting to look at it
what happens when the speed of light
gets huge what the speed of light in
ordinary units is huge that means that
this is negligible in the usual
situations usual situations where the
speed of light is 10 e or 3 * 10 8
m/s the square of the speed of light is
um 3 * 3 is 9 10 * 10 the 17th this is a
huge number in the denominator so for
almost all circumstances this is
negligible also v^2 over C squ is also
negligible the velocity of an ordinary
object is very much smaller than the
speed of
light so this practically reads T Prime
is equal to T Galileo's equation
it only begins to fail when the velocity
gets up near the speed of light so only
when the speed the relative velocities
of The Observers are near the speed of
light does this differ appreciably from
Galileo's T Prime equals T same thing
here when the velocity is much smaller
than C you can ignore this and it's just
good old X Prime is equal to xus
VT it's only when velocities are near
the speed of light that that the
corrections from relativity become
important
uh but they're especially important for
light which does move with a speed of
light yeah let's see if we can see from
these
equations just
directly uh that a light Ray moves with
the same velocity in either reference
frame well we already did it but let's
just do it again
um yeah let's do it
here if x is equal to T A light ray
light Ray
satisfies xal
T if xal
T if xal T this just becomes 1 - V *
T / < TK 1 - v^ 2/ c
that's X
Prime what about t Prime T
Prime again X is equal to t t Prime is
T
minus I think I'm making a mistake I
can't both have x equal T and have the
speed of light not equal to one I think
I want xal CT here H yeah xal CT so this
is C minus
V cus VT over theun of 1 - v^2 over c^ 2
and this is T
Prime
uh T Prime is equal to
tus V / c ^ 2 * X which is CT so that's
CT / square
root which is equal to T * 1 - V /
C / square
root all right so X Prime is this T
Prime is this what is X Prime over T
Prime oh God I hope it works
out no it should be C it should be C
let's multiply and divide by C
here C minus V / C okay okay yeah it is
c - V * tunk 1 - v^
2 but we have an extra factor of C
downstairs so C prime or or X Prime is
equal
to C T Prime whenever X is equal to
CT magic the speed of light is the same
in all reference frames with this
transformation um
the end product
here is the important
thing you can now test this out oh what
about
okay if x equals
CT we've just proved that X Prime is
equal to CT Prime prime a little
exercise is to show that if
x equal minus CT that's a light Ray
going in the other direction that X
Prime is equal to minus CT Prime that's
something else you can check from this
it's also true so that means a light Ray
going in either
direction will move with a speed of
light in either of the two
frames
okay
what's special about these
Transformations namely that light moves
with the same velocity in either frame
and the relationship between the two
sets of coordinates is reciprocal has
exactly the same form except with the
velocity having change sign that's
what's special about them and these of
course are the Lorent Transformations
these were not the way that lorence
derived them in fact I don't even know
that lorence did derive them
uh
so that's special relativity or at least
the portion of special relativity that
has to do with the XT
coordinates
um I think we're about finished
now what I was going to do which we will
do next time is to derive the
contraction of lengths the the dilation
of time and some various uh special
relativity effects uh dilation of time
being the
most interesting one and then move on to
more about the kinematics of special
relativity what proper time is what
momentum is what energy is and so
forth
uh any questions thus far about what
we've done up till now and our next
class is at 6:00 on 6:00 6 o' yeah any
questions about the physics
though yeah going back to your initial
he first jump he said if you were moving
by the gentleman in the middle at the
time that
two same time if you were in the
middle the two flashes got to the middle
you see at the same time right but you
see this
oneing yeah what you're saying
okay let's the thing to do is to draw
draw picture you're saying forget this
guy over here let's talk about somebody
else who happens to pass through this
point over
here he's moving but he sees the two
flashes of light at the same instant of
time right that's what you're talking
about but he's not midway between the
two
observers he doesn't satisfy the
Criterion that he's midway between the
two observers he this one is having Trav
right right so there's no
reason for him over here to say these
two flashes were at the same instant he
sees the light get to him at the same
instant but he's not midway between them
so again he will not call this point
simultaneously this is the point which
is midway between them and this is the
test point for deciding simultaneity
from the moving frame they'll get to him
at the same time say they they were
right right right right because after
all this one is further away from him
than that
one right
good this is a ni this is a nice
construction to go through it's not very
hard all you do is you take xal T which
is the light Ray you say it passes
through the point xal VT plus L and then
work your way backward with a backward
light moving uh like a backward light
Ray until it hits the point x = VT + 2L
and that tells you exactly where this
point is it tells you what counts as
simultaneous in the moving reference
frame that's the key or at least that's
half the key that's half the key to the
lench transformation the other half is
the statement that the relationships
between the two frames should be
symmetrical apart from the change of
sign of velocity those are the two key
ingredients that Einstein
used uh in one form or another these
were the equations these were the
principles that he used and no other uh
to get to this
point okay so if we're
finished we'll move on next
[Music]
time the proceeding program is
copyrighted by Stanford University
please visit us at stanford.edu